<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Saints in England under a cloud; and their glory eclipsed in this life. Or, The case of desertion briefly stated in a few considerations with severall symptomes of the saints decreasing and declining in spirituals. Very usefull in these times, wherein there is much of notion, and little of the power of godliness manifested. Published for the edification of the faithfull, / by W.T. M.G.</title>
            <author>Troughton, William, 1614?-1677?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94871</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1168_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208794</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858762</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858762</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110820</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94871)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 166:E1168[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Saints in England under a cloud; and their glory eclipsed in this life. Or, The case of desertion briefly stated in a few considerations with severall symptomes of the saints decreasing and declining in spirituals. Very usefull in these times, wherein there is much of notion, and little of the power of godliness manifested. Published for the edification of the faithfull, / by W.T. M.G.</title>
                  <author>Troughton, William, 1614?-1677?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 90, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Mathew Simmons for Hannah Allen at the Crowne in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [5] at end.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>W. T. = William Troughton.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 27".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Worship and love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110820:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SAINTS IN ENGLAND under a CLOUD; And their GLORY eclipſed in this Life. OR, The caſe of Deſertion briefly ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a few conſiderations with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Symptomes of the Saints decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and declining in Spirituals. Very uſefull in theſe times, wherein there is much of notion, and little of the power of godlineſs manifeſted. Publiſhed for the Edification of the Faithfull, By W. T. M. G.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Mathew Simmons</hi> for <hi>Hannah Allen</hi> at the Crowne in <hi>Popes-head Alley.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:110820:2"/>
            <p>THe Saints are cloathed with the <hi>Sun,</hi> yet often un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Cloud.</hi> Their path is like the <hi>morning light,</hi> ſhining more and more unto the perfect day, yet they often decline. <hi>Cloudings</hi> are their affliction, and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinings</hi> are their ſinne. To prevent or remedy either, is a great worke. Both are aimed at in this little Treatiſe: wherein the caſe of a <hi>Spirituall declenſion</hi> is diſtinctly ſtated, and the ſymptomes of it clearly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented. So that the Chriſtian Reader comparing his heart and life with this diſcourſe, may either praiſe God for his <hi>growth,</hi> or pray away his <hi>decayes</hi> in grace. <hi>Soul-declinings</hi> are too <hi>viſible</hi> among the Saints in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> And therefore I judge it ſeaſonable to make this or any faithfull Diſcovery and cure of them <hi>legible.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <date>June 9. 1648.</date>
               <signed>Joſeph Caril.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:110820:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:110820:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110820:3"/>
            <head>To his Excellency the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> Generall of the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> forces.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble S<hi rend="sup">ir</hi>;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE God of Armies hath done great things by you as an inſtrument, for the peace and ſecurity of his people in this bleeding Kingdome; I may ſpeak it (without flattery) that you are the glory of <hi>England,</hi> and ſo you will be ever eſteemed by all true <hi>Engliſh-men;</hi> your place is honourable; your birth is noble: but much more your ſpirit which God hath raiſed and fitted for great and honorable acheivements. When
<pb facs="tcp:110820:4"/>
               <hi>Saul</hi> was made King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> the Lord gave him a royall ſpirit fit for Kingly government; and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when your EXCELLENCY was appointed Generall of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Army; a fourefold portion of the ſpirit of wiſdome, courage, and meeknes, was poured out upon you; that you might be as bold as a lyon, and yet as meek as a lambe; which two excellent vertues have ſhined forth in your converſation.</p>
            <p>The Lord hath given large te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to your faithfulneſſe by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unparelled ſucceſſes, ſo that the Army under your EXCELLEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIES command ſince they were firſt modelt'd have not been fruſtrated in any warlike attempt; and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſome diſcontented ſpirits that are engaged to a faction) cenſure your proceedings, yet I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent there is no man that hath a drop of true <hi>Engliſh</hi> blood runing in his veines, or that hath a right
<pb facs="tcp:110820:4"/>underſtanding of the privileges of the ſubjects of <hi>England</hi> but will bleſſe God for you, and make an honorable mention of the very name of the Lord Farfax, and the army under his command.</p>
            <p>You are yet on the ſtage, and many eyes are upon you; he that hath hitherto enabled you to play your part wiſely for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of three bleeding Kingdoms, will (I doubt not) in his own good time bring you off honourably, and all thoſe under your command that are acted by the ſame principles of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique intereſt.</p>
            <p>Tis true (deare Sir) there are divers members of your Army (as there will be in ſuch a numerous bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) that are ſlight-ſpirited and hold many heterodox and unſound opinions, which no ſober Chriſtian can approve of; yet this I can ſpeake (uppon mine owne certaine knowledge) That there is a preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:110820:5"/>publique ſpirited people in your army; a people that mourn for the diviſions of the times; a people that ſeeke the glory of Chriſt and not their owne honour; a people that walke much with God and have a cloſe communion with him; and who recount continually (with much thankfulneſſe) the ſweete providences and diſpenſations of God towards them and the whole Kingdome by them.</p>
            <p>As for your Excellency. It hath pleaſed the Lord to try you ſeverall waies not only by the malitious ſlaunders of open adverſaries, and by your own bodily weakneſſes; but alſo the unChriſtian and ungrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful cenſurings of pretended friends: and of theſe their are two ſorts (i) thoſe that are riged in their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and practice touching, Church goverment, and (2) another ſort who are or were lately menbers of your army that pretend to be above
<pb facs="tcp:110820:5"/>formes, and to have an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary knowledge of divine miſteries but to ſpeake the truth, they are low and carnall and diſobedient to lawfull authority both civill and martiall: and indeed the power of our good God hath wonderfully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, in carying you through theſe great temptations and difficulties with much ſettleneſſe and chearfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit: If the Lord had not been on your ſide (may you ſay) you bad been ſwallowed up ere this; and the proſperity, and happineſſe of three Kingdomes in you: Let the Lord have the glory of this, as hee hath had of his other mercies from your Excellency.</p>
            <p>Sir, I am bold to tender this little treatiſe to your Excellency: if I did not look on you as humble and ſpirituall, I ſhould not preſent it to you, for it is not ſutable to the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and greatneſſe of the world, but to the experience of humble
<pb facs="tcp:110820:6"/>Saints; with whoſe hidden privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and comforts (I doubt not) you are well acquainted. Now the Lord ſtabliſh you in the truth, and bleſſe you and yours with all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and heavenly bleſsings in Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your EXCELL. humbl: and faithfull ſervant W. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:110820:6"/>
            <head>To the Reader;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have obſerved (of late) that the Saints generally through out this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome have loft much of the power, and vitalls of Religion, ſince they entred on needleſſe diſputes; and while ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to live above Ordinances and Formes, they live below God and Chriſt, in and upon the world; and although they offer liberty to others, yet they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (as the Apoſtle ſpeakes) are the bond-ſlaves of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being lull'd aſleep by Satans delufions, &amp; ſo made inſenſible
<pb facs="tcp:110820:7"/>of the want of thoſe reall injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God which they have had in his Ordinances.<note n="*" place="margin">See the Epiſtle of 12. Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to the Reader, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Book inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The cleare Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of the Goſpel breaking forth upon the Indions in new En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet forth by T.S.</note> I have therefore thought it my chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an dutie to publiſh this ſmall Treatiſe (as that which may be uſefull for ſuch Profeſſors, if God give a ſpirit of humility &amp; ſelf-denyall) which though it be dreſſed in a ſimple and homely phraſe, without the varniſh of humane elocution, yet it diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſome ſpirituall experience of the work of Gods ſpirit which infinitely ſurpaſſeth all humane and acquired abilities.<note place="margin">The poore Indians in <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> may ſhame the Profeſſors in <hi>Old En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Others have treated on this Subject in printed bookes: but as I humbly conceive (with due regard to their elaborate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes) they ſpeak not fully to the preſent condition of the Saints, and to theſe times of confuſion, wherein the myſtery of iniquity works in a high mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:110820:7"/>under guilded and ſpecious pretences, and Satan himſelf is transformed into an Angel of light. What ſhall we ſay of this age? it is neither wholly night, nor wholly day with us: but we expect a glorious evening; wee looke for a time when truth ſhall vanquiſh error, and light ſhall ſwallow up darkneſſe. And thoſe that have a name they live and yet are dead, ſhall be plainly diſcovered, and that maske and vizard pull'd off, where with they have blinded many preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Saints, (I meane) their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of high and glorious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, without relation to the blood of a crucified Chriſt, which is not only ſleighted and undervalued by Papiſts and others that live under a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of works: but alſo by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſort of Profeſſors, who have much of the Spirit of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb facs="tcp:110820:8"/>light, and dying to the fleſh and carnall created things in their mouthes, (the Lord Jeſus in the ſufferings of his humane nature is laid aſide as an Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack out of date, or an old ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration or fleſhly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance out of which they are paſſed) And this is that ſpirit of Antichriſt which began to work in <hi>Johns</hi> time, and appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much in <hi>Luthers</hi> time in <hi>Zwenkfeld</hi> &amp; his followers, who judged <hi>Luther</hi> and other faithful Chriſtians to be men of a very low ſtraine, that lived under a carnall adminiſtration upon the letter and hiſtory, not knowing God in Spirit and in myſtery: which is the very language of the manifeſtarians, in theſe daies concerning many precious Saints.</p>
            <p>I ſhall be far from ſtirring up the civill Magiſtrate againſt
<pb facs="tcp:110820:8"/>thoſe that erre in judgment about ſpirituall things (ſo they ſubmit to lawfull Authority in civill things) for this were to thwart the ſtraine of Chriſts Goſpel, which exhorts us to love and forbearance, if perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture the Lord will give them repentance, to the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the truth<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 10.2</note> our weapons (ſaith the Apoſtle) are not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall but ſpiritual<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor 10 4.</note> and my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (ſaith our Saviour) is not of this world, if it were my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples would fight.<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 18.36.</note> Howbeit it concerns every Chriſtian ſoul to mourn before the Lord, and to be earneſt with him in prayer, that he would conſume the man of ſin with the breath of his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrills and that he would throw down the ſtrong holds of Satan, (namely) thoſe horrid errors, and blaſphemies which are crept into the Churches of Chriſt.
<pb facs="tcp:110820:9"/>I ſhall deſire thee (Chriſtian Reader) to read this little book without prejudice, and to avoid jangling and ſtrife, and minde the things that tend to peace and edification. Now the Lord give thee and mee a ſeeing eye, a hearing eare, and an underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heart; Farwell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:110820:9"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Igh <hi>attainments,</hi> and choyce <hi>Communion</hi> with God, are a great <hi>Happineſſe:</hi> ſuch as many Saints come not up to, nor <hi>all</hi> that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they have them, doe enjoy. <hi>Some</hi> judge themſelves on the top of <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> when they are at the foot thereof, they are without <hi>ſinne, perfect, live in the Eſſence of God;</hi> neither Chriſt, nor any of his inſtitutions are conſiderable with them. The Miniſtery is a <hi>deluſion,</hi> the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of the Goſpel, <hi>low
<pb facs="tcp:110820:10"/>adminiſtrations, empt, Cloudes, fleſhly appearances, and dead formes,</hi> righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, faith, are to them of little <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</hi> Immediate <hi>revelations</hi> are onely looked at, the holy Scriptures laid aſide. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Satans <hi>deluſions</hi> are often taken for the Spirits <hi>diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;</hi> and theſe conceit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves all <hi>Spirit,</hi> manifeſt much <hi>fleſh.</hi> Is it not fleſhly <hi>wiſdome</hi> to put down what the infinite <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of God hath ſet up? to ſeek out inventions of out own, and not to be content with the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which is the power of God to mans ſalvation. <hi>Reader,</hi> art thou beyond others in <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, holineſſe, high attainments?</hi> let not thy <hi>tongue,</hi> but <hi>life, declare</hi> it. <hi>Chriſt</hi> had the Spirit not by <hi>meaſure, John</hi> 3.34. he was <hi>annointed above</hi> his <hi>fellowes, Heb.</hi> 1.9. fill'd with all the <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:110820:10"/>of God, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.9. yet he converſed with <hi>ſinners, Matth.</hi> 9.11. pray'd with <hi>others, Luk.</hi> 9.28. frequented the <hi>Aſſemblies, Luke</hi> 4.16. preached to <hi>mixt multitudes, Mark</hi> 6.33, 34. pray'd before <hi>meat, Matth.</hi> 19.19. 15.36. <hi>Communicated</hi> with his diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.29. made uſe of the <hi>Scriptures, Luk.</hi> 4.17, 18, 19, 20, 21. and directed <hi>others</hi> to do ſo. <hi>John</hi> 5.39. How is it then that any ſhould caſt off ſuch du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? Have they more of the Spirit than Chriſt? Are they richer than he? If ſuch <hi>thoughts</hi> lodge in them, the Lord teach them to know <hi>themſelves,</hi> to bee lowly minded, and to eſteeme <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> better than <hi>themſelves, Phil.</hi> 2.3. What <hi>heights</hi> ſoever ſuch ſpeak of, they are in a bottome greatly <hi>benighted and clouded,</hi> decay'd, rather than growne <hi>Chriſtians. Declinings</hi> are dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous,
<pb facs="tcp:110820:11"/>
               <hi>growth</hi> is comfortable. It's matter not onely of <hi>obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> but of <hi>complaint,</hi> that the <hi>power of godlineſſe</hi> is much aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in moſt Saints. Many in <hi>England</hi> have loſt their <hi>firſt love,</hi> it's time for them to remember <hi>former dayes,</hi> and to doe their <hi>firſt works,</hi> leſt ſevere judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments divorce them from their <hi>ſweeteſt comforts.</hi> This little Treatiſe, very ſavoury and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, written with a Dove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Spirit, will diſcover to thee thy declenſions, and direct thee to the ready way of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. Read it with a ſingle heart, and the Lord make it a bleſſing to thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110820:11"/>
            <head>Saints in <hi>England</hi> under a Cloude.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat ſuch as are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and have taſted of the ſpecially love and grace of God, may yet (for ends beſt known to him) be caſt into a ſleepy, and languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition, and brought to a low ebb in their owne ſenſe and feeling, is an experimented and undeniable truth; and hereof we have divers inſtances in holy writ: <hi>Job</hi> was a godly man there was none like unto him; and yet the Lord hid his countenance from him, <hi>and writ bitter things
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110820:12"/>againſt him:</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Job 13.26.</note> and <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Heman</hi> were filled with horror and amazement in the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Lords withdrawing his comforts, and the <hi>light of his countenance</hi> from them: and the Church of Chriſt was once put upon this ſad and diſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, <hi>That the Lord had forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken her, yea her Lord had forgotten her</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 49.14 Cant. 5.6.</note>: Nay in this we have the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> himſelf for an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who (as touching his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature) wanted thoſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible feelings and injoyments of God which he was wont to have: in ſo much that this bleſſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> of mankinde cried out in the bitterneſſe of his ſoule; <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 27.48.</note>? And againe, <hi>My ſoule is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſorrowfull, even unto the death</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 26.38.</note>.</p>
            <p>For our better underſtanding of this truth,<note place="margin">Two ſorts of deſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> and that wee may
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110820:12"/>have a diſtinct knowledge of it according to the Scriptures; we are to conſider two ſorts of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, which differ much the one from the other.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. A reall deſertion.</note> there is a <hi>totall reall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion</hi> and rejection by God; and this is when the Lord har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens the heart of a man (as hee hardned the heart of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Exo. 4.21</note>) and wholly withdrew the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and beames of divine grace from him; the Lord wil call him no more, he will breath on him no longer by the breathings of his Spirit; now this kind of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion true Saints are not cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of, nor ſubject unto; For although there is oftentimes a withholding from them, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and inlargements, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a totall withdrawing of grace<note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 54.10.</note>: for it is grace, and grace only that ſupports them, and bears up their ſpirits in a droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110820:13"/>and diſconſolate condition; it is the power of the Lords grace upon their ſouls, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents ſad diſaſters, and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate attempts which otherwiſe Satan and their fleſh would put them upon.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. A ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of comfort.</note> there is another kind of deſertion, which cannot properly be called a deſertion, but rather a <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> of thoſe ſoul refreſhing manifeſtations, influences, and conſolations of the Spirit, which a Saint hath formerly enjoyed: neither is this totall and univerſall, but partiall and graduall in reſpect of meaſure and degree; a true Chriſtian is never ſo forſaken of God, but he partakes (in ſome meaſure) of the influences, and opperations of the Spirit of grace (though there may not be ſuch heatings and warmings as there have been.) The Sunne
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110820:13"/>(you know) ſhines upon the earth in Winter as well as in Summer, yet the earth is not ſo warmed &amp; heated, nor the trees made ſo fruitfull by the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Sunne in Winter, as in Summer; juſt ſo it is with a Chriſtian: he hath his Winter as well as his Summer ſeaſons, his nights as well as his dayes, his complainings as well as his conſolations; but yet obſerve, that this kind of deſertion (if it may be ſo called) which a Saint is capable of, is rather in his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion than reall; The ſoul-raviſhing object (which is God in Chriſt) is not darkned, or eclipſed in it ſelfe, <hi>God is perfect light and in him is no darkneſſe at all</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">1 Joh. 1.5.</note>: But the darkneſſe is in the underſtanding, or apprehenſive faculty, which is but renewed in part; the fleſh (as a thick miſt, or cloude) interpoſes it ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110820:14"/>the object and our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings (as betwixt the Sunne and our corporall eyes) ſo that wee cannot clearly ſee into the things that are revealed, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend fully the glory of the ſpirituall object.</p>
            <p>The Saints may be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red under a twofold notion,<note place="margin">Saints conſidered in a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> or relation, &amp; this will help much to the clearing of the matter in hand.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. In juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</note> as they are in a ſtate of Juſtification and union with God in Chriſt; and this admits of no change, diminution, or increaſe; the weak Chriſtian is as much juſtified, as much uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God; he hath as much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and propriety in Chriſt (though hee cannot make ſo much advantage and improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it) as the ſtrong Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, who hath a greater degree of faith: the ground and matter of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110820:14"/>juſtification (which is) the <hi>free grace of God</hi> in and by the <hi>blood of Chriſt as Mediator</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.6, 7. Ro 3.24 25.</note> remaines ſure, ſtedfaſt, and unmoveable, (notwithſtanding the daily ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and backſlidings of ſaints) the <hi>Covenant</hi> which they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is an <hi>everlaſting Covenant</hi> of free grace, which cannot be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anulled<note n="i" place="margin">Jer. 32.40.</note> and the bond of their ſpirituall union (which is) the <hi>Spirit of grace and love</hi> is an <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall bond</hi> that can never be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or diſſolved, (as the bond of temporall Marriage may be) God hath betrothed his Saints to him for ever, and hath given them his Spirit to be a <hi>Seale</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.13.</note> and a pledge of his everlaſting love to them.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. In Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> the Saints may be conſidered in their Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and communion with God, which is an effect, or product of their juſtification and union<note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note>:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110820:15"/>now in this the Saints have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of great changes, and alterations; of ebbings and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings (as in the Sea) of increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and decreaſings (as in the Moone;) Their communion with God, and enjoyment of him, is ſometimes greater, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times leſſer, as God manifeſts himſelf to them, and the Sun of righteouſneſſe ſhines on them; you ſhall have a Chriſtian high in communion with God, when hee meets with a ful-tide and freſh-gale of the Spirit<note n="m" place="margin">The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to wind <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.6.</note>, hee goes on merrily in his way, and paſſes over the Red ſea of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, (as it were) with a fore-right winde; but when the wind blowes not at all, or elſe blowes but ſoftly, either he cannot hoiz ſaile, or at the beſt heeds forced (having but a ſide wind) to tacke often about, and make many boords, before hee get to ſhore.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:110820:15"/>
            <p>Here you may aske me why Saints now under the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament adminiſtration,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Queſt.</note> are leſſe ſurprized with ſpirituall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhings, and ſwoonings than Saints (were) under the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament adminiſtration?</p>
            <p>The old adminiſtration in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendered bondage,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> and terror in thoſe who lived under it; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were ſonnes, yet were they dealt with as ſervants; though they were heires, yet were they uſed as children in nonage<note n="n" place="margin">Gal. 4.1, 2, 3. Gal. 5.1.</note>: but the new admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration brings peace and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Saints: This the Apoſtle handels excellently (as in other places,) ſo eſpecially in the 2 to the <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 <hi>Chap.</hi> Therefore thoſe Chriſtians that act much from a ſpirit of bondage, and yeeld to ſlaviſh feares, &amp; terrors (though they may be right in the maine) yet doubtleſs their carriage and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110820:16"/>demeanour is not anſwerable to the new Teſtament adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Now the reaſon (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) why <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and other eminent believers in the old Teſtament, had ſo much horror upon their ſpirits, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they lived under a typical adminiſtration, and were types of Chriſt;<note n="*" place="margin">God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things to believers under the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Types and ſhadows, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1.</note> not only in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſufferings: but alſo in their ſpirituall agonies, and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; in the one they ſhaddowed forth the ſufferings of his body;<note n="*" place="margin">Vide Calv. Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Cap. <hi>11.</hi> Sect. <hi>3.</hi> ad finem.</note> and in the other the ſufferings of his ſoule; And now the old adminiſtration being aboliſhed, and a new one taking place; we doe not read, that the Saints who lived ſince Chriſts aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, have had ſo much horror and bondage upon their ſpirits, as <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>David</hi> had.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe (it cannot be denied, but) the Saints have their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110820:16"/>ebbings, and languiſhings under the new Teſtament more, or leſſe: <hi>Paul</hi> that choſen veſſell of God had <hi>conflicts within, as well as terrors without;</hi> he was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes carried up into the <hi>third heaven</hi> (as he writes of himſelf)<note n="o" place="margin">2 Cor. 12</note>, but had ſometimes experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſad qualmes, and aguiſh fits; and in <hi>Johns</hi> time, which (according to the opinion of ſome) was a time of more light, The Angels of the <hi>Church of Epheſus</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Rev. 2.4, 5.</note>, (who were faithfull, and ſo acknowledged by Chriſt himſelf, in the 2, and 3, verſes) had loſt their firſt love, and were fallen from their former zeale; and therefore Chriſt bids them remember from whence they were fallen, and repent, and doe their firſt works; So that in the pureſt times the Saints have had their cold fits, their retrogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations and goings back in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualls.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:110820:17"/>
            <p>Thus much for the proofe of the premiſſes; now that the weak ones may not be offended at this diſcourſe, for I would not will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly offend, or ſtumble any that profeſſe the name of Chriſt, it will be neceſſary to premiſe a few cautions,<note place="margin">4. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations by way of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> for preventing miſtakes, and informing the judgment a right, before I come to the Symptomes; and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der there unto, I ſhall lay down theſe following conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as Satan (that lying ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) may delude thee,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Conſi.</hi> Satan will tempt you to think worſe of your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition than it is.</note> by flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee into a beliefe that thy ſoule is in a flouriſhing &amp; grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition (by reaſon of ſome gifts and enlargements) when it is otherwiſe, and thus he deales with hypocrites, and temporary believers; ſo may he likewiſe accompliſh his wicked deſigne, by perſwading thee, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110820:17"/>thou art in a languiſhing condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion when thou art not; by the <hi>one</hi> he would puffe thee up, and make thee glory in the fleſh, and by the other he would expoſe thee to ſuch diſcouragements, that thou ſhouldeſt not ſerve God comfortably in thy calling: as hee will tempt thee to think better of thy condition than it is; ſo likewiſe to think worſe of it than it is; by preſenting before thee falſe mediums, and glaſſes, and putting thee upon conſulting with fleſh and blood, which is no competent judge in ſpiritualls, <hi>for the fleſh ſavoureth not the things of God</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 16.23.</note>.</p>
            <p>Now this latter temptation of Satan commonly ſurprizeth a Chriſtian, when he hath a deep ſenſe of his own vileneſſe, and is much abaſed in himſelf, &amp; his heart in an humble and contrite frame; for then 'tis moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110820:18"/>ſuch a temptation may take a deep impreſſion; therefore at ſuch times, take heed you deny not the work of grace, and the operation of the Spirit of God upon your ſouls; acknowledge your own nothingneſs, but with all be ſenſible of the love of God towards you, in changing and renewing your hearts.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Conſi.</hi> The keen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a corruption doth not infallibly preupoſe a declenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualls.</note> it cannot be ſafe for a Chriſtian to judge of his ſpiritual condition by the keen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or activeneſs of this, or that corruption in him for the ſoul may have intimate converſe and familiarity with God; and be filled with that peace which paſſeth underſtanding, when (yet) it is buffetted, and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the bublings up, and ſtirrings of corruption; and this was <hi>Pauls</hi> caſe in the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Rom. 7.</note> where after a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict with the fleſh, hee comes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110820:18"/>off a conquerer by the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>victories of Chriſt:</hi> and in another place<hi rend="sup">r</hi> he tells us that he had a thorne, or prick in the fleſh (which was ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table corruption or other) and though hee had prayed thrice againſt it, yet ſtill it continued vexing the good man, to the end that his faith &amp; patience might be exerciſed, and therefore the Lord tells him for his comfort, that <hi>his grace was ſufficient for him</hi> (notwithſtanding the malice of Satan, and the daringneſs of his luſts) and that the <hi>Lords strength was made perfect in his weakneſſe</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.</note>. Here <hi>Paul</hi> was not in a ſpirituall conſumption, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was exerciſed with the ſtirrings of corruption: but (therefore) God permitted it that he might not truſt in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: but in the Lord; ſo neither ſhouldeſt thou preſently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110820:19"/>(upon the ſtirring of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry corruption) that thou art run behind hand in true mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for as ſome Patients that are nigh unto death make a great buſtling, and are ſo ſtrong when they are giving up their laſt breath, that two, or three men can ſcarſe hold them; or as the body of a man after he hath received his deaths wound, will leape, and move from place, to place; even ſo it is with the luſts and corruptions of believers; for though they are knockt in the head, and have received their deaths wound by the death of Chriſt, yet will they buſtle and make a ſtir, ſo long as wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in this Tabernacle, and untill the fleſh be perfectly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued in us by the Spirit.<note place="margin">3. <hi>Conſ.</hi> The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the body hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal actings</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the conſtitution of the body (if diſtempered with melancholy, and other ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110820:19"/>may and doth cloude the underſtanding, and interrupt the internall motions and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the renewed ſoul; So that a Chriſtian cannot clearely apprehend them in himſelfe, or make out the ſame to others. Melancholick Chriſtians are as full of divine experiences, as heavenly and ſpirituall as any; yet when this duskiſh humour, and black diſtemper of melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly (which may well be called the devils cuſhion) is prevalent upon them; oh what falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions! what groſſe miſtakes and carnall reaſonings! what cloſing in with Satans ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and fighting under his coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, doe theſe bewray at ſuch times; how ſhameleſſe are they in denying what Chriſt hath done for them, and what the Spirit hath wrought in them, and evidenced to them; which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110820:20"/>they will thankfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, when the skie is clear &amp; the weather faire, when the cloude of melancholy is diſpelled, and the foggy miſts of temptations ſcattered; and therefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves Saints not to judge of their ſpirituall condition, in melancholick and pettiſh fits, for the Satan and their owne lying hearts (joyning together) will deceive them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Conſ.</hi> Saints differ in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall growth.</note> as ſome trees grow taller and ſhoot forth more than others; ſo is it with Saints in their ſpirituall growth: there are Saints of ſeverall degrees, and meaſures, as there are <hi>ſeveral gifts and diſpenſations, and but one Spirit</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.</note> ſo there are ſeverall degrees of faith, love joy, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and all (even the leaſt) of them ſtreaming from that one Spirit; <hi>Unto every one of us is given grace according to the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110820:20"/>meaſure of the gift of Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Eph. 4.7.</note>. Some have more, and others leſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the wiſe diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Father; perhaps thou art not ſo high in communion with God as others are; thou haſt not high attainments, but art low and dead hearted, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring thy ſelf with others, wilt thou therefore conclude, that thou haſt no communion with God at all, or that there is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of thy communion with him? that thou art no member at all becauſe thou art not the moſt eminent member? or that thou art a languiſhing dying member, becauſe thou art not ſo nimble and active in ſpirituall performances as others? Theſe are falſe concluſions, and ſhew forth a great deale of pride and unthankfulneſs.</p>
            <p>Thus much by way of caution, now I come to the <hi>Symptomes</hi> of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110820:21"/>a Chriſtians abatement in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualls; in the handling whereof I ſhall be ſomewhat large.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Symtome</hi> If there be a decay of love, humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity &amp; ſelf-denyall.</note> if there be a decreaſe, and abatement of ſpiritual love, humilty, and ſelf-denyall; ſo that you grow ſleight and envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and high minded, truly it is a ſad <hi>Symptome:</hi> it may be, you have great gifts, and excell in outward performances, &amp; high and lofty expreſſions, of more than ordinary enjoyments of God, as if yee only did reigne, and none were comparable to you, and yet (all this while) you walk proudly, and vainly, and whilſt you boaſt of high attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, you live much below God; Thus it was with ſome in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.7, 8.</note> who looked on <hi>Paul</hi> and the other Apoſtles, as not worthy to be compared with them in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all enjoyments, and here upon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110820:21"/>the Apoſtle makes uſe of that ironicall expreſſion (which wee may take up in our dayes) <hi>Now yee are full; now yee are rich, yee have reigned as Kings without us, and I would to God that yee did reigne, that wee alſo might reigne with you.</hi> [I would it were ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, (as you ſay) that we might beare you company and ſhare with you in your enjoyments] But theſe very <hi>Corinthians</hi> were ſo far from excelling the Apoſtl (in a ſpirituall way,) that they were much below him, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked carnally; <hi>Are yee not carnall</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>for as much as there are diviſions among you, and I could not ſpeak to you as unto ſpirituall, but as unto carnall even as unto babes in Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.1</note>.</p>
            <p>Now in this there may be great miſtakes, and therefore take theſe <hi>rules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, if you have greater en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110820:22"/>of God than your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 1. The clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er appre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>henſions you have of God, the viler you will be in your owne eyes.</note> you will then ſee more into the evil of your own hearts and bewaile the ſame; doubtleſs the more you ſee of God the viler you will be in your owne eyes; if God appeare unto you in his glorious perfections; you cannot but lie in the duſt, in the ſenſe of your owne filthineſſe, and imperfections: and for this we have divers inſtances in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: when the Lord had invail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his glory to <hi>Job:</hi> how did it humble and abaſe him? <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaid he)<note n="z" place="margin">Iob. 40.4 5.</note> 
               <hi>I am vile, what ſhall I anſwer thee? I will lay my hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my mouth, once I have ſpoken but I will not anſwer, yea twice but I will proceed no further.</hi> [I will expoſtulate the caſe with God no longer, neither will I plead mine owne righteouſneſſe with him.] And againe,<note n="a" place="margin">Chap. 42. verſe 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>I have heard of thee by the bearing of the eare,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:110820:22"/>(that would not move him) <hi>but nowmine eye ſeeth thee</hi> [now I come to ſee thy glorious Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes and perfections, thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving opened mine eyes by thine owne Spirit] <hi>wherefore I abborre my ſelfe in duſt and aſhes.</hi> And ſo <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> when he ſaw the <hi>appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the likeneſſe of the glory of God,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ezek. 1.28.</note> 
               <hi>he fell on his face;</hi> in token of humility, and ſelf abaſement. And the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> when he ſaw that glorious viſion <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.5. cryed out in the ſenſe of his owne vileneſſe, <hi>We is me for I am undone, becauſe I am a man of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane lips, mine eyes have ſeen the King the Lord of hoſts.</hi> If you have ſeen the Lord in his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous appearances, oh your hearts will be humble, your conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces tender, your ſpirits full of ſelf deny all; the viſions of God &amp; Chriſt will (above all other things) throw downe the pride
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110820:23"/>of the fleſh, and cauſe the ſoule to have a high eſteeme of the Lord Jeſus, as the chiefeſt of <hi>ten thouſand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Rule</hi> The more precious will the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Goſpel be to you</note> the more precious and beautifull will the word and Ordinances of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be to you, (as Preaching, Prayer, Sacraments, Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints) I dare ſay, if you enjoy much of God (as you ſay you doe) you will be ſo far from ſleighting the Ordinances of God (under the notion of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and fleſhly diſpenſations) as that you will have higher thoughts of them than you have had the Lord Jeſus powring out his comforts upon you in and by theſe as conduitpipes) you will remember that you have had ſweet meetings with God, heavenly breathings and warmings, unſpeakable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and refrſhings from him;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110820:23"/>and that God hath unvailed, and uncovered his face, and appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed gloriouſly unto you in theſe adminiſtrations; and therefore the word and Ordinances of Chriſt will be precious to you as <hi>gold</hi> and <hi>ſweeter unto you than honey, and the honey combe</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſa 19.10</note>. And indeed it doth not a little amaze mee, that any who profeſſe the name of Chriſt and union and fellowſhip with him, ſhould abandon the Ordinances of Chriſt (now under the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament) ſeeing <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes Prophetically (in reference to this latter adminiſtration<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 84.1, 2, 3, 4. &amp; the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Mica.</hi> chap. 4. verſ. 1, 2.</note>) of the amiableneſſe of Gods Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles, and the Saints long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after God in the uſe of his Ordinances. Hath not the Lord refreſhed your ſoules in Prayer, and raviſhed your hearts, while you have communicated with the Saints in a Sacrament? and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110820:24"/>have yee not by an eye of faith (in the uſe of an Ordinance) <hi>ſeen Jeſus</hi> Chriſt crucified for your ſins, and ſitting at the right hand of his Father making interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for you? ſuch as have expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the Communications of God can ſet to their ſeales that this is true, and therefore take heed of ſleighting thoſe adminiſtrations, wherein you have found God ſo abundantly.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Rule</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation will be more holy i, in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> if you have high en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of God in the Spirit, your converſation will excell in ſpirtualneſſe, and holineſſe, by the irradiations of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, yea, there will be ſuch Chriſtian care, and watchfulnes, that you will flie from the very appearance of evil, from the garment ſpotted with the fleſh, from fleſhly tamperings, lacivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous geſtures, and unprofitable diſcourſes; where the Spirit of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110820:24"/>God works moſt there will be the greateſt conformity to God (who is holineſſe it ſelf:) But to deſcend to particulars.<note place="margin">2. More particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. You will be in a good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the world.</note> your affections will be in a high degree crucified to the creature: true mortification conſiſts not in a few good words; and fine expreſſions, for there are many that ſpeak much of dying to the fleſh, and carnall things, who yet live much in the fleſh and upon the world; really therefore to be crucified to the world, is to have the heart and affections alienated from it, and ſet upon God and heavenly objects; <hi>our converſation is in Heaven</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle)<note n="e" place="margin">Phil. <hi>3.20.</hi>
               </note> and wee ſit together with Chriſt in heavenly places, and <hi>I am cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the world and the world to me</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note>. (That is) I am ſo <hi>dead</hi> to the world that it is indifferent to me, whether the world ſmile
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110820:25"/>or frowne upon me; for I care no more for it, than it cares for me; and againe, <hi>They that are Chriſts have crucified the fleſh with the affections and luſts</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Gal. 5.24</note>.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. You will be tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted to the lambes of Chriſt.</note> you will exerciſe abundance of Chriſtian love, meekneſſe and tenderneſe of ſpirit towards the Saints, even the weak ones, that ſcruple the lawfulnes of ſome things (which you are reſolved in:) you will beare with them, &amp; be exceding loath to offend them; <hi>Paul</hi> was a very high Saint, hee came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde none in ſpiritualls nay, he excelled all his contemporaries; and yet how compaſſionate and tender hearted was hee to the weak ones? in ſo much, that he writ a whole chapter to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> upon this ſubject<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 14.</note>; &amp; truly this was that frame of ſpirit which appeared in Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; in all his tranſactions on
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110820:25"/>earth, he gave a ſtrict charge to <hi>Peter</hi> to feed his lambs (his little ones) and puts the evidence of <hi>Peters</hi> love upon this; And how full is that expreſſion of his to our purpoſe, <hi>I have yet many things to ſay unto you, but you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not beare them now</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Io. 16.12.</note>. Intimating, that he would ſpeak to them as they were able to beare; he had milk for babes, and ſtrong meat for ſtrong men: And that other ſaying of our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſhews his exceeding great and tender care of his little ones<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 28.6</note> 
               <hi>whoſoever ſhall offend one of theſe little ones which believe in me, it were better for him that a millſtone were hanged about his neck, and that he were drowned in the depth of the ſea.</hi> Surely theſe Chriſtian affections, and tender bowels are much wanting in ſome Profeſſors, who care not how much nor how often they offend and ſtumble their weak
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110820:26"/>brethren (as they tear me them) by their unſavory words, and ſcandalous walkings.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. There will be more pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in your ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for truth.</note> it will appeare fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in your ſufferings for truth; if you have a high communion with God there will be much divine power, heavenly wiſdom, and ſelf denyall, expreſſed in your ſufferings &amp; perſecutions: for, according to the meaſure of your communion with God, and conformity to Chriſt your head, ſo will your carriage and demeanour be in time; of ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: If therefore you manifeſt much pride, and turbulency of ſpirit, and conſult much with fleſh and blood at ſuch times; it ſeemes you are but low in your apprehenſions of God, &amp; your attainments are not ſo great as you would make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome.</note> another <hi>Symptome</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:110820:26"/>may be this;<note place="margin">If you reſt much in the ſtreames, &amp; ſeldome goe to the fountaine.</note> If you can content your ſelves &amp; reſt ſatisfied with the ſtreames, without going to the fountaine, and well-head: perhaps you looke further than the bare outſide, and ſhell of an Ordinance (as praying hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c.) to thoſe refreſhings and communications which you meet with in Ordinances, but yet you live below the authour and fountaine of them, in as much as you live and feed on that which is diſpenſed &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated in an Ordinance, and not on the Lord himſelf who is the diſpenſer of it, and the fountaine form whence it flowes and is derived unto you; and this is to live on ſomething below God, who is the onely ſoul ſatisfying good: Now hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites and carnal Goſpellers may have ſome kind of joy, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing and delight in Prayer,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110820:27"/>and hearing, as thoſe in <hi>Iſaiah</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 58.2.</note>, and the <hi>ſtoney ground,</hi> which for want of root withered away; As wee ought not to live on our owne actings, or apprehenſions, ſo neither ought wee to termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate our joy on thoſe quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and enlivenings which wee meet with in Ordinances; but on him who is the God of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and the God of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation: If therefore you can warme your ſelves at the fire of inlargments and elevations of ſpirit (kindled in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of duties) its a <hi>Symptome</hi> you rather decreaſe, than grow in ſpiritualls: for a woman to content her ſelfe with the gifts, &amp; love-tokens of her husband, or bridgroome, and to let out the ſtreame of her affections on theſe, without minding the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of her husband, its no good argument, that ſhe hath ſtrong
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110820:27"/>affections to her husband, ſo neither doth it argue that you have an intimate communion with God, if you can ſatiate, and glut your ſelves, in a few love tokens; (namely) thoſe heat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings &amp; meltings of ſpirit, which you have experience of in your performances.<note place="margin">3. ſad E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffects, flow from this.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now this produces three ſad effects;</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. Self ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting and carnall boaſting</note> it produces vaine car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall boaſting, and ſelfe exalting (if not in words yet) the frame and bent of the heart runs in that channell; there is a ſecret inward ſtroking, and admiring of ſelfe; and applauding of gifts, inſtead of the rich love of God (which only puts the difference between you and others.<note n="*" place="margin">Amat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde hoc habet ſed ipſe eſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de amat <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note>)</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. Sleight nes of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</note> from hence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds that <hi>rugged, ſleight,</hi> and <hi>ſuperficiall</hi> frame of ſpirit, (when the heart hangs looſe from God
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110820:28"/>and is indiſpoſed to ſpirituall things) and of this the Saints are very ſenſible, and do exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly bewaile it; for whilſt their hearts remaine in this frame every temptation, and every car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall object ſeizes upon them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. Sad qualmes &amp; preſſures of heart.</note> this alſo produceth <hi>ſad qualmes, and ſoule-oppreſsing diſtempers:</hi> if you will be ſetting up <hi>Idols</hi> inſtead of <hi>God,</hi> and give that honour to them which is due onely to God, I can aſſure you (from mine owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) you will meet with ſad-after claps: there will be a great &amp; ponderous weight (I meane) much guilt upon your ſoules, your conſciences will miſgive you, &amp; accuſe you, though your Idols may be ſweet in the mouth, yet will they be bitter in the belly; the end will be bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe, and you will <hi>lie downe in ſorrow</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Iſa. 50. laſt.</note>: God will put water in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110820:28"/>your fire, and extinguiſh it; ſuch joyes as ariſe from falſe grounds (are but like the crak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thornes under a pot) and will not long endure.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome.</hi> If the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of men tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port you.</note> if you be deeply affected and tranſported, and that conſtantly with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of men (and namely) ſuch as are in ſome meaſure ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall; yee waite for it, and when it comes, yee can ſwallow it downe (as a ſweet morſell) and glory (in this) that you are counted more eminent than others; and on the contrary, you greive as much when other Profeſſors are in more credit, and in greater repute for their ſpirituall gifts, &amp; endowments, than your ſelves: Wee read that the other Diſciples were highly offended, with that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of prefetring <hi>John</hi> &amp; <hi>James</hi> before them, and that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110820:29"/>(among themſelves) which of them ſhould be the greateſt; and <hi>Johns</hi> Diſciples<note n="n" place="margin">Joh. 3.</note> were angry, that Chriſt and his Diſciples, ſhould have more followers and admirers than their Maſter, whereby they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated that they were but babes in the knowledge of Chriſt: but as for the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> himſelf, it ſeemes hee had much of God in him, for he ingenouſly acknowledged, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt increaſe and himſelf decreaſe, neither did hee repine, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and was glad that Chriſt the Bridgroome was exalted, whoſe meſſenger and ſervant he was. This ſeeking honour of men was the great let, &amp; obſtacle in the way of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> ſo that they could not believe in Chriſt; <hi>How can yee believe which receive honour one of another, and ſeeke not the honor that commeth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110820:29"/>from God only</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Joh. 5.44.</note>? and indeed this was the <hi>break-neck</hi> ſin of <hi>Diotre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes,</hi> for the Apoſtle writes of him, that hee affected the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence (that is) to be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more excellent, then the Apoſtles and their followers; that ſo, he might make a world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gaine of his ſpirituall gifts: and if it be thus with you, that you are taken with the applauſe of men, and love to have the preheminence, it is a <hi>Symptome</hi> that you are in a ſleepy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; want that ſpiritual ſenſe of your own nothingneſs, which you have formerly had.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome.</hi> If you kick a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> reproofe.</note> if your hearts be haughty and ſtubborne, ſo that you will not take a reproofe kindly, and meltingly, but kick againſt it, and your brethren that admoniſh you; and inſtead of an ingenious acknowledgment of your fault, yee frame excuſes,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110820:30"/>and your ſpirits ſwell, and grow big upon it; I'ts evident (in this caſe) that God hath hid his face from you, and thus it was with <hi>Peter</hi> that holy man, who (when the Damoſell charged him home with truth) he grew outragious, and paſſionate, and no marvell, if he took it no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from her, for the good man was left to himſelf, that he might have experience of his owne weakneſſe, and learne to put his confidence in the Lord. After Chriſts aſcenſion (when there was a greater effuſion of the Spirit upon him, &amp; the myſtery of faith was more clearely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to him) we doe not read that he was ſo vaine, and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate, under a reproofe (when <hi>Paul</hi> withſtood him to the face for his double dealing<note n="p" place="margin">Gal. 2.11.</note>:) Wee may therefore conclude, that thoſe Profeſſors who ſpurne at
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110820:30"/>their brethren for giving them a ſeaſonable reproofe, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, and (upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt) grow ſtrange to them, and refraine their ſociety, are much under a cloude, and in a great meaſure carnal, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the reproofe of a Saint would be as oyle powred out on their heads, and it would be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained as a meſſenger from God.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, when there is a neglect,<note place="margin">5. <hi>Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome.</hi> When you are formal in your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> (or ſuperficiall uſe) of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an duties, and ſervices; <hi>I</hi> have obſerved two extreames in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors: ſome doe idolize the meanes, and ſet up Miniſters and duties in the place of Chriſt, (as if theſe were crucified for them:) and others ſleight du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Ordinances, as dead formes, beggerly rudiments, carnall adminiſtrations, fleſhly appearances; and thus it was in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110820:31"/>the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>one ſaid he was of Paul, another of Apolle, another of Cephas;</hi> here was ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing men, and meanes, but then there was another ſort, that ſaid they were of Chriſt, that is (as I conceive) in oppoſition to men, and meanes; they were ſo for Chriſt, and his imediate teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and diſcoveries, that they ſleighred the faithful diſpenſers of the Goſpel, and neglected all meanes, and Ordinances as the teachings onely of man, and not of God.<note place="margin">Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from a twofold conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall only mention a double conſideration from which ſome Profeſſors neglect Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Conſi.</hi> That there is a going out to the world which is diſtinct from the Church of Chriſt.</note> becauſe there is: going out to the world, and diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Word, and Prayer to the world; therefore Saints may not communicate therein; This is a groſſe miſtake and (I hope)
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110820:31"/>there are not many of this judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for,</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. No difference of places under the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</note> there is no difference of places, neither are wee tied more to one place than to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other (now under the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament) ſince that typicall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe that was in the Temple is aboliſhed, and thus much in effect our Saviour told the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Samaria</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ioh. 4.21.</note>. Truth is truth, and the Goſpel is the Goſpel whereſoever it is diſpenced; as one place is not more holy than another, ſo neither is one place more unholy than another, in the dayes of the New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. Chriſt preached to the world and Saints did accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him.</note> Chriſt preached to the world, to the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> to all ſorts of men, and embraced all places, occaſions, and opportunities, to declare the will of his Father, and his Diſciples (who were Saints)
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110820:32"/>were with him, and heard him, and <hi>Paul</hi> and the other Apoſtles preached often in the ſhipps to the rude Sea-men, and donbt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, ſome of the Saints did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company them, &amp; were preſent at their exerciſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. Saints may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon praiſe the Lord, who hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veredthem out of the world.</note> by that doctrine which is delivered to the world; yee that are Saints (who me the Lord hath taken out of the world) may have occaſion mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to praiſe the Lord, and to magnifie the riches of his grace, (who hath put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween you and the world, and hath tranſlated you out of the kingdome of darkneſſe, into the kingdome of his deare Son:) yee have no excellency which you have not received, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore why ſhould ye boaſt as if ye had not received it? why ſhould ye inſult over thoſe that are in a naturall conditin and have
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110820:32"/>not yet attained to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the myſtery of Chriſt? I am ſure the Goſpell teacheth you another leſſon, and if yee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the voyce thereof, yee will be tender hearted, and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate towards ſuch as are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, ſeeing they cannot helpe themſelnes till grace over po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer their hearts: <hi>the ſame power that raiſed Chriſt from the grave enables a poore ſoule to beleeve in Chriſt.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Epehſ. 1.19.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſome truthes which are diſpenſed to the world, are in a ſpeciall manner uſefull for ſaints; as the doctrine of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and reconciliation by the blood of Chriſt, and the doctrine which holds forth the evill, and ſinfulneſſe of ſin; the ſaints are not come to ſuch a perfect knowledge of theſe truthes, they do not ſo fully ſee into the miſtery of ſin, and the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110820:33"/>glory of their redemption by Chriſt, neither doe they ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and cleerly aprehend the offices and relations of Chriſt, but much more may be added to their knowledg of theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Conſi.</hi> That the Scriptures hold forth a perfect viſion of God in this life. Iſa. 60.19. Reve. 21.</note> this ſlighting of ordinances and duties proceeds from a miſaplication, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpretation of ſome ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (which hint at the ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ordinances) as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 60.19. and <hi>Revel:</hi> 21. <hi>The ſunne and moone</hi> (which ſome conceive to be the Ordinances of Chriſt) <hi>ſhall ſhine no longer but the Lord will be an everlaſting light to his church;</hi> now if theſe ſcriptures bee appliable to the Church earth (which I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinke ought to be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the ſaitns when glorified and triumphant in heaven) it muſt be when he church is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110820:33"/>made perfect, not onely by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, but inherently when ſhe ſees God face to face, and there is no fleſh nor corruption in her; till then, they ought not to plead for an exemption from Ordinances; and if Ordinances ceaſe in this life, much more eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drinking, and the duties of matrimonial relation; if there ſhall be ſo much glory revealed, as to ſwallow up the former (which are of a higher nature) that fulnes of glory, will (much more) put an end to the latter, which are lower, &amp; more periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and therefore thoſe that ſay, they need uſe Ordinances no longer, let them alſo refraine from eating and drinking, and converſing in the world.<note n="*" place="margin">Praeſens haec vita, vita eſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei, quae non eſt praeſentum ac fruenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſed ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentium, ſperantium &amp; expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antium.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, if yee conſtantly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the pureſt Ordinances, and the moſt ſpiritual and evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Miniſtery, and heare truths
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110820:34"/>that are moſt ſutable to your condition, and coreſpond moſt with your experiences, and yet bring forth little or no ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al fruit, but are ſtill dead-hearted indiſpoſed, and unprofitable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe thriving diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: its a <hi>Symptome</hi> that you are under a ſpirituall diſtemper<note n="*" place="margin">Non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredi eſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredi.</note> Chriſtians oft times blame the men, and the meanes, and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with the truths of God, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as too high or too low for them, when they oght rather to blame the carnality, ſleightnes and unbeliefe of their owne hearts; for herefore <hi>the word profits not becanſe it is not mixed with faith in them that heare it.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Heb. 4.2.</note> (yet I deny not) but there may be and often is,<note n="*" place="margin">Sermo auditus fine fide vel fide non mixtus tâ abeſt ut proſitaudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enti, ut magis eum damnet. <hi>Muſcul.</hi>
               </note> a great failing in him that diſpenſes the word, for he may deliver it ſo generally, and confuſedly (having little or no experience of the worke of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:110820:34"/>Gods Spirit) that an experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Saint cannot profit by it. If there be not bodily motion, and ſtirring, you may conclude the party is in a ſwound, or trance, and againe, if he eat good victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls and thrive not by them, but rather grow lank and leane, you may well ſay he hath an ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, by reaſon of ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily diſtemper or other; So if the word be purely preached, and the truths of the Goſpel diſtinctly handled, and you at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the meanes from day to day, and ug continually with your hearts, in Ordinances, and yet (notwithſtanding) you finde little or no ſpirituall ſap, and moiſture, but are leane and drie (in this caſe) it is evident enough that your ſpirituall digeſtion is in a great meaſure gone from you, and that your inward man is under a diſtemper: Now this
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:110820:35"/>may be, when (yet there is as frequent an uſe of Ordinances, as much praying, hearing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring, in the letter and forme as ever: but there wants that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life, and vigour, that holy familiarity, and boldneſſe with God in your performances, which was wont to be, nay your performances (by the breathings of the Spirit) may be lively and ſpirituall to others, and yet your ſelves (in the meane while) dead-hearted, and labouring under the burthen of your Iuſts: the great crop of gifts, and fluent expreſſions which you have uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally had in Prayer, &amp;c.) may ſtill remaine, and yet that which is the life of Prayer (Goſpel faith and aſſurance may decay, and this many Chriſtians can tell you by experience.<note place="margin">7 <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome.</hi> when ſaints ſhark much after creature comforts.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, this may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Syptome,</hi> if yee dote ſo
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110820:35"/>far on creature enjoyments, that in dallying with theſe, you ſpend and ſquander away many preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous houres, and dayes, without ſerious thoughts of God, and heavnly intercourſes betweene him and you, and ſo commit Idolarries with the creature, and run a whoreing after the world and earthly things; <hi>Forſaking</hi> (him who is) <hi>the fountaine of liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing water, and digging to our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves broken ciſternes that will hold no water.</hi>
               <note place="margin">x<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Jer. 2.13.</note> If you ſet your hearts on creature beauty, and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice your affections, to wanton dalliances igh apparel, diet, buil dings, and other creature excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, ſpending the very ſtreame, and creame; and quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of your affections, on theſe periſhing objects, ſo that when you come to rejoyce in God, and love God, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things, yee have no heart to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110820:36"/>it, but are altogether dead and indiſpoſed (as to this) having ſpent your affections upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther objects, and tired out your ſelves in the things of the world, and further, if you can rejoyce exceedingly in the poſſeſſion of theſe outward things, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row as much in the want of them, (be it a husband, a wife a child, or any other creature that is deare to your) as if your life and happineſſe were bound up in theſe temporall enjoyments, Its aparent to me, that you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe not much with God, but (rahter) that his countenance is hid from you: and ſurely the Prophet <hi>David</hi> was much under a cloude, and not ſenſible of the conſolations of his God, when his affections were ſo captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and inſnared with the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Berſheba:</hi> and good <hi>Ezekiah</hi> was in the like condition, when
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:110820:36"/>he made ſhew of his <hi>gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve</hi> (in a vaine glorious manner) to the King of <hi>Babylon.</hi> And for thoſe Chriſtians that are eaſily tranſported, and ſurprized with every temptation, &amp; drink much of the periſhing waters, it appeares their ſpirits hang looſe from God: they have but little ſpirituall joy, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they run out to creature comforts, and ſo <hi>ſpena their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for tht which is not bread, and their labour for that which ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">If. 55.2.8 Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, If there be an abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in poynt of aſſurance.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Eighty, if your aſſurance of ſalvation be weakned, your evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences blurred, and your ſoules brought into bondage, ſo that you fall (as it were) under a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of works, by poreing too much on your ſelves, and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and not eyeing Chriſts blood and righteouſneſſe in the Spirit: Now the ſoules that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:110820:37"/>hath been acquainted with Chriſt the true ſpirituall ſeed, may yet goe back to a Covenant of works, (as <hi>Abraham</hi> hankered after <hi>Iſmael,</hi> who was a type of the Covenant of works, even when <hi>Iſaac</hi> that typified the Covenant of grace was borne) and that two wayes.</p>
            <p>First,<note place="margin">1. In de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on eternall acts.</note> in depending on the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall acts of Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and deriving your peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from the work done;<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex opere operato,</hi> which is meere Popery.</note> and hence it is that you are lifted up, and caſt downe according to the outward performance; thus the <hi>Phariſees</hi> builded their hopes, and comforts upon their doings and performances, and ſo doe many Profeſſors in theſe dayes,<note place="margin">2. Of the internall motion in ſtead of Chriſt.</note> who (whileſt they depend on their owne righteouſneſſe) <hi>are the greateſt enemies to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of Chriſt</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in a more refined
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:110820:37"/>myſterious way, attributing that to frames of ſpirit and to the acts of faith, love, joy, (which ſome falſly call <hi>God in them</hi>) which ſhould be attributed only to the righteouſnes and blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of the Lord Jeſus; If you fall on any thing for life &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation (though never ſo ſpeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) beſides the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, as Mediator, or if you looke on any thing either exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall without you, or internall within you, as a ground of your peace, apart from or without relation to the blood of Chriſt (whereby the ſame is rendered acceptable in the ſight of God) this is to fall under a Covenant of works, and oh that this were but rightly conſidered by thoſe who count, the knowledge of Chriſt in his <hi>Mediatorſhip,</hi> and <hi>Preiſt-hood,</hi> to be no other than
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:110820:38"/>a knowledge of him after the fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Rom. 8.14. <hi>Yee have not received the ſpirit of bondage againe to feare;</hi> how then can the Saints be brought into bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and under a Covenant of works?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> Tis true, the Spirit of God having once ſpoken peace to a believer, he doth not afterwards bring him into bondage, by tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him that he is under wrath, and in chaines of darkneſſe; for this were a plaine contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is far from the Spirit of God <hi>(who is truth and is no lye)</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">1 Joh 2. <hi>c</hi> 7.</note> nevertheleſſe the Saints may be brought into bondage after they have received the Seale of the Spirit, (as they may alſo be deluded with errors) which wee muſt not impute to the Spirit of God, but to Satan and the fleſh, for theſe two joyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:110820:38"/>to rob God of the glory of his grace. The Spirit (who is free in his operation) cauſeth terror, and ſlaviſh feare in the believing ſoule, no other wayes than the Sunne cauſeth darkneſs by ſuſpending his beames and irradiations, doubtleſſe ſo far as wee hearken to the ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and language of the Spirit of God, wee ſhall be conducted into the way of truth, peace, and comfort: but wee often give credit to Satan that lying ſpirit and ſo are led from Chriſt, the true way into <hi>dangerous paths;</hi> Suppoſe yee take counſel both of an honeſt-man, and a deceiver ſo far as you follow the adviſe of the honeſt-man, yee proſper well in your buſineſſe, but if you will be tampering with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe of the deceiver, (which is our caſe then wee have to doe with Satan, who is the great Jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler)
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:110820:39"/>yee will be cozened and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded.</p>
            <p>Ninthly,<note place="margin">9 Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, If ye ſlight the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints.</note> if the ſociety and communion of Saints eſpecially ſuch as keep cloſe in their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, and are moſt ſpirituall, holy, and watchfull in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, be tedious and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome unto you, ſo that you forſake their aſſemblies, and meetings, <hi>as it was the manner of ſome in the Apoſtles dayes,.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 10.25.</note> And though yee are convinced that they have much of the Image of God upon them, and your hearts have been wonderfully expatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and enlarged, whilſt you fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented their aſſemblies, (God having unboſomed his love to you, in the communication of their experiences) yet now your ſpirits ſwell and riſe up againſt them, as too ſtrick, and too watchfull for you: not long
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:110820:39"/>ſince their company and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was delightſome and precious unto you; oh you could not be abſent from them an houre; you were never in your right element but when you were converſing with them: I appeale to you; did not your hearts often burne, and were not your affections raiſed hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven wards in communicating with them? where then is your former zeale and love, ſeeing now yee are as much or more affected with the company of meere worldings, or lukewarme Goſpellers, or ſleight ſpirited Opinioniſts, than with the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of theſe precious ſaints? certainely they have but could affections to Chriſt, who looke on the communiion of ſaints, as an arbitrary, indifferent thing; And as this is a <hi>ſymptome</hi> of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying in ſpiritualls, ſo it argues
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:110820:40"/>much vanity and ſlightneſſe of ſpirit, if you be taken up in your meetings with circumſtanciall and triſling things, and ſo fall to jangling and ſtrif,<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe bleſſed truthes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Saints concur, and agree, as (namely) the Doctrine of Juſtification by Chriſt, of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance by the ſpirit, and liveing upon God by ſaith in our ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall callings and relations: and herein profeſſiors doe as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren uſe to do who looke more on the outſide than on that which is with in, and prize ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and toyes more than Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clous things.</p>
            <p>Religion (which conſiſts in a conformity of the hart to God) is now turned into a diſpure, and made uſe of only as a head notion; [a ſad thing]: hee that is the greateſt diſputant, and can utter bigg ſwelling,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:110820:40"/>words is counted the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Chriſtian; whereas many diſpute much of religion, that manifeſt but little of the power of it: and thoſe that are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and walke circumſpectly, can tell you from experience, that they have ſeldome (or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) mett with the comforts of God in diſputes, but have come away from them with ſad harts, and drooping ſpirits and how can it be otherwiſe, ſince men exalt their owne notions and gifts more than Chriſt, and ſtrive more for victory than for truth in contending for their opinions.</p>
            <p>Thirdly when men are let looſe to a ſpirit of bitterneſſe,<note place="margin">10 Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, If there be much bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting brethren.</note> invie, and parſecution So that they ſtuff and fill their bookes, ſermons, and diſcourſes, with gall and wormeword, and rake up all the dunghills they can
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:110820:41"/>meete with, that ſo they might find a matter againſt brethren, (who in ſome things oiffer from them) looking on that which is true Chriſtian charity (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Apoſtls deſcription)<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.</note> as want of true zeale: ſuch a ſpirit as this hath acted much of late in profeſſors (that live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeuerall formes) and indeed ye that have a cloſe commuinon with God &amp; a cleere judgment in the things of God, may ſee theſe angry bitter men (that would violently obtrude upon their brethren every opinion they hold though but Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanciall under a penalty) not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their heat of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, grow exceeding colde in the practicall part of Godlineſſe, and in the duties of Chriſtian Charity; while they continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cry out errors errors &amp;c. without excerciſeing bowells of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:110820:41"/>compaſſion towards their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, they themſelves looſe much of their Communion with God: for whereas they ought (in tenderneſſe of heart) to pray and mourne for their brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (if fallen into any error either of doctrin or practiſe) and endeavour (by meekneſs of ſpirit to ſet them in joynt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaint:<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>So the word fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, Gal. 6.1. in the Greek.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>columitati naturae di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentia me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicorum ſervit ita Chriſtiana Charitas ſanitati mentium &amp; cordium tam reſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dae quam retinendae ſubſervire debet.</note> they rather revile them, and raile at them in a publique way; and it is very obſervable, that divers miniſters, and others whoſe faces have formerly ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the glimpſes and rayes of Gods countenance upon them) &amp; whoſe diſcourſes have ben exceeding ſavory, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall: ſince they fell upon this violent and railing ſtormy, and promoted ſelfintreſt, their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits have ben flat &amp; dul, their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes generall and confuſed, and their ſociety uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:110820:42"/>neither is there that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life, and vigour in them that was wont to bee: If the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall parts of a mans body bee weakened you will ſay hee is in a conſumption: it is ſo in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls when there is not that life, of faith, love, joy, &amp;c. in the ſaints, which they have manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in times paſt.<note place="margin">11 Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, If there be a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> departing from the ſimplicitie of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Againe if ye depart from the ſimplicity of a Crucified Chriſt, and cry up every new notion, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very vaine opinion, as a glorious diſcovery of God &amp; are unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bied, and unſetled, (like ſo many wandering ſtars, &amp; waves of the ſea) being toſſed to and from with every winde of Doctrine, &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to change your Religion and principles every day, (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the judgments of men with whom yee converſe) Its a ſymptome that ye are but babes and infants in the Knowledge of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:110820:42"/>Chriſt for it is the Property of children to be much affected with new things for a little while, and then to caſt them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way againe for other toyes: Thus it was with ſome mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the churches at Corinth and Galatia, who (it ſeemes) were unſtable Chriſtians, and much given to novelties, (and therfore a great trouble &amp; vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation to the Apoſtle) for no ſooner was he departed from them, but they were taken with new doctrines, and run after the falſe Apoſtles, diſreliſhing both the perſon and Doctrin of <hi>Paul,</hi> in ſo much that he breaks out into that vehement interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to the <hi>Galathians</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Oh fooliſh Galathians who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiched you that you ſhould not obey the truth,</hi> as if he had ſaid; I left you in a good condition; when I was laſt with you, you did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110820:43"/>the goſpel of Chriſt; but ſince my depature, ravening wolves [Satan and his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments] have been among you, and they have bewitched you, with their falſe doctrines. And againe, have yee begun in the ſpirit and will you end in the fleſh? with many other paſſages to this purpoſe in his epiſtle to the Churches: So that it was not the leaſt worke which <hi>Paul</hi> had to do, to ſettle and ſtabliſh Chriſtians in the Doctrine of Chriſt; after they had ſubmitted to it; nor was it the leaſt of his ſuffrings (nay it was a heavy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction to him, as it is to every faithfull diſpenſer of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) that after all this paines, and care &amp; trouble and ſuffrings in there behalfe, they ſhould depart from the ſimplicity of that Goſpel, which hee had boldly preached and contended
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:110820:43"/>for<note n="*" place="margin">Noſtra bac aetate inven as inuumeros, qui cam E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelium Dei, audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſent mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabili quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, &amp; ardo-reſpiritus in amorem illuis exar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerint, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtea vero per falſos featres cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumventi conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t. onem ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis ſuae non ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in fide ac ſpiritu Chriſti, ſed in juſtitus carnis quarere coepermt.</note>, the mother after ſhee is delivered of her child, is put to as much trouble in nurfing and educating it, as ſhe was in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it forth; So was <hi>Paul</hi> in a ſpirituall ſence, he had many throwes and panges after he had begotten them to Chriſt: nay he falls in travaile with them again <hi>my little children</hi> (ſaith he) of whome <hi>I travaile in birth againe till Chriſt be formed in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wonder not that profeſſors in theſe daies are cold and dead hearted, and that they ly open to the violence of every ſtorme and every temptation for how can it be other wiſe with them ſo long as they play faſt and looſe with truth and depart from the true rocke and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
            <p>But for your better infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in this point I ſhall heere lay downe two cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:110820:44"/>
            <p>Firſt (notwithſtanding what hath beene ſaid) yee ought not to content your ſelves with this or that meaſure and degree of faith,<note place="margin">Two cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. 1. Reſt not in the meaſure you have attained to.</note> and knowledge it the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Goſpel, as ſome profeſſors do; who (fearing they ſhould fall into error, and be deluded with <hi>new lights</hi> as it is called<note n="*" place="margin">Learned <hi>Zanchy</hi> cals it a new &amp; heavenly light.</note>) remaine ſtill in their old formes,<note place="margin">Si igitur ſentimus in animis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris novu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; celeſtem lucem ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſam, &amp;c In expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. ad E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. fol. <hi>47.</hi>
               </note> and meaſures; as if nothing could be added to their knowledge in ſpirituall things; wee ought (neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe) to take heed of laying new foundations, and taking <hi>up</hi> new Goſpels; <hi>for no other foundation can any man Lay then that which is Layed</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 3</note> and if <hi>an Angell from heaven preach any other Goſpel let him be accuſed</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> every faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtian <hi>holds to</hi> the true foundation; though hee cannot argue againſt every thing that croſſes the foundation, or vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:110820:44"/>every truth which hee is convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of, yet he cloſes with that heavenly Martyr that ſaid, <hi>though he could not deſpute for Chriſt, yet he could dy for Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Caution.</hi> Cenſure not thy brother upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly neither ought yee to cenſure Chriſtians as Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtats, for reiecting ſome things which they formerly embraced, for this they may doe and yet not change the foundation or cry up another Chriſt, but it may be they have more light, and knowledge, and a cleare judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning, the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the ſuperſtructure, or matter to be builded theron: that whereas they have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly builded hay &amp; ſtubble, <hi>&amp; ſuch like combuſtible matter</hi> (which ſhal be conſumed by the fire of the ſpirit of God<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.12.</note>) they now build <hi>Gold and ſilver and preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones</hi> (that is) true Doctrine, and faithfull workes upon the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:110820:45"/>true foundation.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly,<note place="margin">12 Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome. If ye live more on the acts than on the object of faith, love, joy.</note> if you caſt your eye more on that which is inherent in you, as your faith in Chriſt, your love to God, your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſpirituall things, which are weake, and imperfect (for yee know but in part yee beleeve but in part, yee love but in part) then on the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, which the Lord in his infinit love, and grace hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto you, It appeares that you are not much acquainted with the myſtery of the Goſpel, neither do yee give that honor to Chriſt (the obiect of faith) which is due to him; for ſhould theſe graces (or rather effects of grace) have a greater traine, more attendants, and a fuller Court then that glorious righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, (which is layed up for you in Chriſt) ſhould theſe which are but hand-maides and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:110820:45"/>ſervants) have greater reſpects, and be more honoured in point of aſſurance, then the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Chriſt which is the Queene and miſtris of them all? this were to give more honour to <hi>Hagar</hi> the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide, then to <hi>Sarah</hi> her miſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. If you ſhould doe thus in outward things, it would bee counted one of the greateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civilities; how much more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable is it in heavenly and ſpirituall things: Faith and love are but hand-maides, &amp; ſhould be ſubſervient to Chriſt who maintaines the court, and is at all the coſt and charge: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for you to aply your ſelves to theſe and neglect Chriſt, (which is a courſe that many poore ſoules take) ſhewes you to be but young Courtiers in the <hi>pallace</hi> of heaven, and to have little familiarity with the King of glory.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:110820:46"/>
            <p>Againe this may be another Symptome of your declining in ſpiritualls, if you reſt in a few teares,<note place="margin">13 Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome. If ye reſt in your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints &amp; ſorrowes.</note> and complaints (which ſome falſly conceive to be true ſorrow and repentance for ſin,) we have many profeſſors that will be proud in complaining of their pride, hipocriſie and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart; and yet they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore and worſhip this under the notion of true humilitie, and ſelfe denyall, and ground and bottome their peace and happineſſe upon it; having made their complaints and expreſſed a few ſorrowfull words, that they want faith, and have hard hearts, &amp;c. they repoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on this rotten ſtaff, and have continuall recourſe to it, as an evidence of their good eſtate: but what ſaith our Saviour, <hi>not every one that ſaith, Lord Lord</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 7.21, 22.</note> [I am ſo, and ſo, I have a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:110820:46"/>hard heart, a hypocriticall heart, a proude heart,] <hi>ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Kingdome of heaven but he that doth the will of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> (that is) he that beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in God, through Chriſt; for that is the greate <hi>Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement: and to beleeve in God is to do the will of God, and worke the workes of God</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 6.29.</note>. If you have taſted of the love and bountie of the father, and of his dainty diſhes, and ſoule satisfying de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, and can now feede on theſe low things, (I meane) a few teares, and complants; its a Symptome ye are run behinde hand in Spiritualls. A begger that hath had good cheeare at a gentlemans houſe, will not ſit downe ſatisfied with a few empty words, and bare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, <hi>but he muſt have bread and bread he will have before he departs:</hi> The promiſe is not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:110820:47"/>made <hi>to him that compla neth but to him that commeth</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 6.37</note>; nor is it ſufficient <hi>to thirſt after the water of life,</hi> and to complaine and cry for it, (as Eſaw cryed for the bleſſing and ſought it with teares) but ye muſt come and drink of it, if ye wilbe refreſhed and ſatisfied<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 6.35</note>: <hi>Ho every one that thirſteth Let him come and buy wine and milke without money and without price</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 55.1.</note>.</p>
            <p n="14">14 When you are exceeding ſtrange,<note place="margin">14 Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome. If ye be ſtrange &amp; reſerved to Chriſt your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</note> and reſerved, and have not that enlargedneſſe of heart, towards Chriſt your husband and bridgroome, which you formerly had; the time hath beene you have layen in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and had ſweete embraces from him, and have been <hi>kiſſed with the kiſſes of his mouth, and refreſhed with the flagons of his wine</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Cant. 1.2.</note>; and not onely ſo, but you have been open hearted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:110820:47"/>him, and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the ſecrets of your hearts to him, yee kept nothing from him, that might ſerve to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the reality of your love and the vehemency of your affections to him, but behold now yee are growne ſtrange, and ſly, and take ſtate upon you, and are not free to unboſome your ſelves to your husband, this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates you have other lovers beſides that you dally with, and impart your mindes unto (if I may ſo ſpeake) and withall it apeares that you trad not much with your ſpirituall husband: Yee know if a wife be reſerved to her husband, and yet famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or with other men, it may well bee thought that ſhee hath but cold affections to him: and it is as true in this caſe, <hi>Chriſt hath eſpouſed you to himſelfe, hee hath purchaced you by his blood, and you
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:110820:48"/>are united to him by his ſpirit:</hi> and will you let out your hearts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter other lovers and give them the beſt entertainement you have, whilſt hee ſtands at the doore and cannot be admitted? this carriage (as it doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſpouſe of Chriſt) ſo it ſhewes that ſhee is declined in her affections and reſpects to Chriſt, and ſo it was with the ſpouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Cant. 5.3.</note> when ſhee put off her husband (who came to viſite her in love) with idle excuſes, ſhee was halfe a ſleepe, and halfe waking, and therefore did not tainde the worth of him that came to give her a viſit, and waited to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to her; but when ſhee was perfectly out of her ſleepe, and knew it was the voice of her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, ſhee runs after him, and inquires of all the perſons ſhee mett with, where her beloved
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:110820:48"/>was, that ſhe might goe to him: And you that are now aſleepe (if the Lord awaken you and move your affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s by putting in the <hi>finger of his ſpirit at the hole of the doore</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Cant. 5.4.</note>) will be as reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe as ſhee was to renew your acquaintance and communion with your beloved.<note place="margin">15 Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome. If yee yeeld to fullenneſſe of ſpirit, and refuſe comfort.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly if there be ſuch a dogg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe and ſullenneſſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in you, that you will not be comforted, like <hi>Rachell</hi> in her impatient moode, or like little children (<hi>which Chriſt alludes to</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 11.16, 17.</note>) who are ſo ſullen and pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh that whether you <hi>pipe or mourne</hi> to them, how ever you deale with them, whether by faire or by fowle meanes, they will continue wrangleing, if they have not every toy they would have: perhaps God deals with you by afflictions, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives you of creature injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:110820:49"/>(which were a great block in your way) this doth not pleaſe you but you grow impatient, and repine at this diſpenſation: and if he abound to you in outward things, and afford you much outward peace, and proſperity, ye wax wanton alſo under this diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, no condition, neither that which you are in, nor that which you long after, will keepe your harts in an even, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall frame: truly if it be thus with you, it argues you have a loathing ſtomack, and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable to a ſurfit, there is a ſuperfluity of naughtineſſe in your harts which muſt be purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, ſuch as will wrangle and quarrell with every diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God and make impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vement of none (as it is the caſe of ſome ſoules that are in fullen fits) it ſeemes to me they
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:110820:49"/>want the <hi>light of Gods counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> which (being bid from them) makes them impatient and ſullen, as the ſpouſe is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered: with the abſence of her husband, who by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence puts her into a pleſant moode, and contented frame.</p>
            <p>Haveing layed downe theſe 15 Symptomes (wherin I have beene ſome what large becauſe they are ſutable to theſe deſerting times) I ſhall now give you <hi>three grounde or reaſons,</hi> why there are ſuch eclipſes or cloudings of Gods countenance.</p>
            <p>Firſt becauſe the ſpirit of God, which is <hi>a ſpirit of wiſdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ground.</hi> The Spirit of God is free wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</note> 
               <hi>and revelation, a ſpirit of life and light, a ſpirit of love and of a ſound minde</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 1.17. 2 Tim. 1.7</note>, is a free and arbitray a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, he workes when, and where, and in what meaſure he
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:110820:50"/>pleaſeth; as the <hi>wind bloweth where it liſteth ſo the ſpirit workes where and how</hi> he pleaſeth<note n="b" place="margin">John 3.8.</note>: to ſome he reveales more, to ſome leſſe of the minde of God none are perfect in there faith, love, joy, while they remaine heere: as he is free to give the ſoule comfort, and ſpeake peace to it, ſo he may as freely withdraw his divine influence from it, (at leaſt in ſome meaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) and who can blame him for ſo doing ſince he acts freely, and every dram of peace, and comfort (which any poore ſoule hath) is meerely of grace and benevolence: if you have more communion with God then your brethren; and a bound in the comforts of the holy Ghoſt whilſt they morne under ſad diſcouregments, you have ſo much the morecauſe to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the grace of God <hi>for what have
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:110820:50"/>you which you have not received?</hi> as the ſun is free in ſhining on your outward man, ſo the ſpirit of God is alſo free in caſting his beames upon your inward man.<note n="*" place="margin">Donum ſpiritus liberum eſt, nulli meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to alliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. <hi>Muſc.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the Lord (in his infinit wiſdome) layes you low,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Ground.</hi> Saints are brought low, that they may ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize with their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</note> that you may pittie others that are in a ſad conditon, (over whome you would otherwiſe inſult and triumph) ſuch as have knowne the terrors of God, and have beene in the depths of ſorrow, and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves, will Sympathize with there afflicted brethern: experience makes a compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate and tender hearted Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: if ye be wounded your ſelves, you would be ſenſible of others: if you be exerciſed in the ſpirituall warfare your ſelves you will pitty thoſe that by groaning under the burthen
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:110820:51"/>of corruption; by exerciſe wee come to be expert <hi>ſouldiers</hi> in the Campe of Chriſt &amp; indeed the ſpeculative part of religion, is not comparable to the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call: our Saviour himſelf was <hi>tempted that he might be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsionate high preiſt and know how to helpe others that are tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note>: you are apt to grow proud, and wanton, when you have much comfort and greate rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, you are puffed up with your inlargments, and looke at your poore wounded afflicted brethren, at a great diſtance: the Lord (it may be) will take away your comforts, and put you into the ſame capacity with them, that you may be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of their ſorrowes: no temptation hath taken others but it may alſo ſurprize you, yee may ere long (for ought I know) mourne after your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:110820:51"/>as the Spouze did in the Canticles; though you have the bridgrooms preſence now with you it may be ſhortly taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, and then your countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wilbe ſad, and your harts be filled with ſorrow; you ought therefore to be ſo far from cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring your diſconſolate bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as that you ſhould morne with them, and helpe to beare their burthens <hi>&amp; ſo fulfill the law of Chriſt;</hi> which is a law of love.</p>
            <p>Thirdly becauſe God will put a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the meaſure,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Ground.</hi> God will have Saints know they have not a full poffeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of heaven here.</note> of the Saints enjoyments here, and in glory, here they live by faith, there by ſence and viſion, here their comforts ebbe &amp; flow, but there they have an uninterrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed communion with God, a fulneſſe of joy in the beatificall viſion of the Lord of glory: 'tis true the ſaints in this world have experience of that joy,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:110820:52"/>which is unſpeakable, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but they have but a taſt of it, ſome times they are ſo carried up in the ſpirit as that the moſt excellent things in the world are as nothing unto them: but theſe raptures are not of long continuance there is as great (if not a greater) dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, betweene the Saints here, and the Saints in glory, in the meaſure of there joyes, as betweene the Saints that lived under the old adminiſtration, &amp; thoſe that have liv'd ſince <hi>Chriſts</hi> aſcention, when he diſtributed great portions of his ſpirit to the ſonnes of men<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 4.8.</note> as princes uſe to give great gifts at the time of their coronation: the Apoſtle cleares this excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13: 12. <hi>now wee ſee darkly through a glaſſe or medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> [now wee have but a Darke ſight of the glory of God] but
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:110820:52"/>then (namely) when the vaile is rent and corruption ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, wee ſhall ſee face to face, <hi>now wee know but in part but then wee ſhall know even as wee are knowne;</hi> the failings and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the moſt ſpirituall Saints, do ſufficiently confeſſe the vaine interpretation which ſome give on this place, (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) that the perfect viſion of God is to be referred to the Saints there, which cannot be obtained without a change of the outward man; this mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty muſt put on immortality and this corruption incorruption at the glorious appearance of the ſonne of God, when <hi>the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhal be delivered up to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the father ſhal be all in all</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> 
               <hi>now we are the ſons of God, it doth not appeare what we ſhalbe, but wee know when he doth appeare we ſhall
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:110820:53"/>be like him for wee ſhall ſee him as hee is</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 John 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>hee ſhall change our vild bodies that they may be faſhioned like his glorious body</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 3.1 21</note>: and this is that which the Saints long after as the great marriage feaſt, the complement of their joy and happineſſe, praying conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, <hi>come Lord Jeſus come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> Spurne not at this Doctrine as too low, and carnall for you: let not ſuch a thought enter into your hearts, but examine your ſelves ſtrictly concerning it, that at length (if it be the will of God) yee may be ſenſible of your great loſſe: for a man to be wounded and not know it, aggravates his afflictions; to be miſerable &amp; yet to be ignorant of it, adds to his iniſery: the time was when you had tender conſciences; broken and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite hearts, and were ſenſible of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:110820:53"/>the ſtratagems of Satan, and the deceitfulneſſe of your owne ſpirits, yee have alſo ſeene the out-goings of God, and your mouthes have beene filled <hi>with mirth and</hi> ſinging as the bird in a ſummers, morning; oh how pleaſant and delightfull have the truths of God, and Saints of God beene to you, but now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold (and oh that you were ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of it) yee walke in a deſart and wilderneſſe where there is no water: darkneſſe is your habitation; you feed on chaff and windy notions in which there is no ſubſtance no reality; your underſtandings are cloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, hearts hardened, your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences benummed your ſpirits (like Tinder) apt to take every impreſſion of Satan, and all this, becauſe the <hi>bridegrome hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne himſelfe from you,</hi> he is gon behinde the curtaine: the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:110820:54"/>ſun is ecclipſed, &amp; tis night with you: and what ſaies our ſaviour; if a man <hi>walke in the night he ſtumbles, and if the light that is in thee</hi> [namely the underſtanding which is the light of thy ſoule] <hi>be darkneſſe oh how great is that darkneſſe</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">2 Mat. 6.22.</note>! In this ſad conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you may take up that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of <hi>Job</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Job 29.2, 3, 3, 4, 5, 20, 25.</note> (who had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the Lords hiding his face from him) <hi>my harpe is turned into mourning &amp; my organ into the voice of thoſe that weepe, and wiſh (which him) that you were as in the months paſt as in the daies when God preſerved you, when his candle ſhined upon your head, and when by his light you walked through darknes, when the Secret of God was upon your Tabernacles, &amp; the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty was yet with you, when your glory was freſh in you and you were as thoſe that comfort the mourners, when you did ſee the power and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:110820:54"/>of God in the Sanctuary</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſa. 63.2.</note> 
               <hi>and your harts were ſweetely drawne out unto him becauſe of the ſavor of his good ointments</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Cant. 1.2</note> 
               <hi>namely the glorious rayes of his countenance which ſhined upon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> 2. To conclude if you would bee reſtored to your former comforts, and injoyments or greater, I beſeech you (and oh that God would enable you by his grace) to looke up to Chriſt by an eye of faith, and claſp faſt about him: It is not all your prayers, and teares (though I doe not ſay theſe or any Goſpel ordinance wherein Chriſt manifeſts himſelfe muſt be neglected) it is not your gifts and parts, nor any of your performances, that can reſtore you but only the Lord Jeſus apprehended by faith: how comes the heart to be filled <hi>with joy and peace</hi> but <hi>in beleeving?</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:110820:55"/>and againe <hi>beleeving yee rejoyce with</hi> joy unſpeakable and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<note n="i" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8.</note>: for your incouragement (let me tell you that) ye have a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der hearted Saviour to deale with; one that hath aboundant experience of your ſorrowes one that knowes what it is to have the countenance of God eclipſed: goe to him and plead before him the promiſes, his death, his reſurrection, his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious offices &amp; relations, &amp; call to minde former experiences of his love and goodnes <hi>he died for</hi> you <hi>when you were enemies to him;</hi> and will he not give you a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous viſit now that yee are his friends? <hi>he was found of you when you ſought not after him</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iſai 65.1</note> &amp; wil he not manifeſt himſelf to you now that you ſeeke him by faith? hee knowes very well that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be without him, having once
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:110820:55"/>had communion with him, and therfore hee will anſwere you when you call, he wil open when you knock and both <hi>hee and the father will come and ſup with you</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Iohn 14.</note>: he cannot be long from you for yee are his jewells, and ingraven upon the palmes of his hands, yee are members of his body<note n="m" place="margin">Epheſ. 5.30.</note> 
               <hi>and can he forget his owne fleſh and blood?</hi> its impoſſible: what though yee have rebelled againſt him? yet conſider that <hi>hee loves you freely and will heale your back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidings for his anger is turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from you</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Ioſea 14.4.</note> 
               <hi>his thoughts are not as your thoughts, nor his wayes as your wayes</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Iſa. 5.1.</note> having once ſet his love upon you, hee will never take it off againe: hee may (in his heavenly wiſdome) for a while hide his face from you, that you may prize his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the more when you have
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:110820:56"/>it: take heede of an evill heart of unbeleefe in departing from the liveing God: to whome will yee goe (I pray you) for <hi>hee only hath the wordes of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 6.68</note> hee that hath wounded you muſt cure you; nay hee will do it if yee will but come to him <hi>him than cometh to mee I will in no waies caſt out.</hi> Now the Lord drawe you by the Cordes of his love<note n="q" place="margin">Hoſ. 11.4.</note> that you may come to him and finde reſt in your ſoules <hi>not in the act of your coming</hi> but in the perſon <hi>whome yee come to,</hi> for he is the <hi>eternall reſt of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:110820:56"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <label>A.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ALterations</hi> not alwayes cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable. <hi>p. 67</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Applauſe p. 35</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Aſſurance</hi> weakned <hi>p. 51</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Attainments,</hi> reſt not in what you have <hi>p. 66</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>B.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bitterneſſe</hi> againſt thoſe, differ in judgement, ill. <hi>p. 59</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>C.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Communion</hi> of Saints ſlighted. <hi>p. 56</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Comfort,</hi> ſuſpenſion of it, <hi>page 4.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sharking after Creature-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts <hi>p. 48</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Converſation,</hi> whoſe moſt holy, and mortified. <hi>p. 27</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Corruption,</hi> the keeneſſe of it, doth not certainly ſuppoſe declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in ſpirituals. <hi>p. 14</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:110820:57"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Covenant</hi> of works, now many goe back to is <hi>p. 52</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>D.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Deſertion,</hi> totall and reall, what, <hi>p. 3</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Diſtempers;</hi> bodily Diſtempers hnider ſpirituall actings. <hi>p. 16</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>F</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Faith;</hi> not the acts but objects of it, to be leaned upon. <hi>p. 68</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Formality</hi> in duties. <hi>p. 39</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>G</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Goſpel;</hi> the ſimplicity of it, not to be departed from. <hi>p. 62</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Growth:</hi> the meaſure of ſpirituall growth different. <hi>p. 18</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>H.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Heart:</hi> tender-heartedneſſe to the weak. <hi>p. 28</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Heaven:</hi> no full poſſeſsion of it here. <hi>p. 81</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Humility:</hi> thoſe moſt humble have cleareſt apprehenſions of God. <hi>p. 22</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>I.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Injoyments:</hi> Great and high in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments
<pb facs="tcp:110820:57"/>of God, how knowne. <hi>p. 21, 22,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>O</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ordinances,</hi> to whom pretious, <hi>24.</hi> Why ſome neglect them. <hi>p. 40, 44</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>R.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Reproofe p. 37</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rigteouſneſſe</hi> of Chriſt onely to be looked at. <hi>p. 53</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>S</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Saints</hi> conſidered, as juſtified, as ſanctified. <hi>6, 7, 8.</hi> leſſe ſubject to bondage now than under the old Teſtament. <hi>9.</hi> They have their ebbings. <hi>p. 11</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sorrowes</hi> not to be reſted in. <hi>p. 70</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Spirit:</hi> whether Saints may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſpirit of bondage, <hi>54.</hi> A free agent. <hi>p. 77</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Strangeneſſe</hi> to Chriſt. <hi>p. 72</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Streames:</hi> ill to affect them, and neglect the fountain. <hi>31.</hi> Sad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it. <hi>p. 33</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sympathizing. p. 79</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:110820:58"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sullenneſſe. p. 75</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>T.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Temptations:</hi> Satan tempts to think better or worſe of ones ſelfe, than it is. <hi>p. 12, 13</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>V.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Unfruitfulneſſe. p. 46</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>W,</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Weak:</hi> who are tender-hearted to them. <hi>p. 28</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:110820:58"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>FOr lacivious page 26. read laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious. Imediate p. 40. r. immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate. <hi>Preſemum</hi> pag. 45. r. <hi>preſemium.</hi> Our ſelves p. 49. r. your ſelves. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution p. 59. r. perſecution. Ptactice p. 61. r. practice. He could not diſpute p. 67. r. <hi>I</hi> cannot diſpute, yet <hi>I</hi> can. Familior p. 73. r. familiar. Sence p. 82 r. ſince. Saints there p. 83. r. Saints here. Morning p. 86. r. mourning.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
